Preliminary Guide to the Anthropology Department records, 1973-1992 RG0086
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Anthropology Department records
1973-1992
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
RG0086
1 Linear Feet
This series is a collection of reports and "Anthro notes" newsletters. They range in date from 1979 to 1986.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Acquisition information is unknown.
Historical or Biographical Note
Anthropology is the study of the forms and functions of human diversity in the present and the past. Through intensive fieldwork and laboratory analysis, anthropologists compile detailed knowledge of particular populations, develop theoretical generalizations, and test theoretical claims against empirical evidence gathered in one or more locales. In its broad focus on humanity, anthropology is an integrative discipline, bringing together scholarly work in the humanities, natural sciences, and social sciences.
The Anthropology Department at The George Washington University (GW) was founded in 1965, and is committed to integrating the humanistic and scientific perspectives of the discipline while pursuing advanced research of the highest quality. It believes that research should be both rigorous and creative, and that it should be intrinsically connected to our activity as teachers. Moreover, research and teaching activities of Anthropology faculty members should resonate with and complement each other. The department supports undergraduate and graduate students being provided with outstanding classroom and practice-based training in the "four fields" — archaeology, biological anthropology, sociocultural anthropology, and linguistic anthropology. A GW degree in anthropology should signal that the holder is experienced in synthesizing diverse kinds of data about human beings, a skill increasingly valued in a variety of professions as well as in academic settings.
The program encourages team-teaching and experimentation with new teaching methods and technologies because these approaches feed back directly into cutting-edge research. Similarly, the department eagerly seeks out professional collaboration within and beyond the University in order to create the kind of vibrant intellectual community that stands at the heart of any great research institution.
The late Colin Turnbull was a prominent faculty member in the department in the 1970's and 1980's.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include reports and "Anthro-notes" newsletter and vertical files materials. They range in date from 1973 to 1992, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Anthropology Department.
Collection Organization
Organized into two series. They include the "Anthro-notes" newsletter and Departmental files.
Bib#
8186805
Anthropological linguistics; Physical anthropology; Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Washington (D.C.); George Washington University; George Washington University. Dept. of Anthropology
- Report and newsletter, 1979-1986; RG0086 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is a collection of reports and "Anthro notes" newsletters. They range in date from 1979 to 1986.
  Formerly ACC#35
  - Report of the Anthropology Department, 1988 ca. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Includes "Plans and Priorities for Implementation for 1988-89."
  - Anthronotes - A Newsletter for Teachers, 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Departmental files, 1973-1992; RG0086 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series includes brochures, flyers, and reports. They range in date from 1973-92.
  Formerly vertical files
  - Anthropology Department, 1973-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Student Manuals, 2004-2011; Series 3
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains graduate student manuals for the anthropology department, 2004-2011.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Anthropology Graduate Student Manual, 2004-2005; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anthropology Graduate Student Manual, 2005-2006; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anthropology Graduate Student Manual, 2008-2009; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anthropology Graduate Student Manual, 2009-2010; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anthropology Graduate Student Manual, 2010-2011; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)